<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | rodrigolima.github.io]]></title>
  <link href="https://rodrigodlima.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://rodrigodlima.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-11-27T02:42:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://rodrigodlima.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rodrigo de Lima Silva]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="https://rodrigodlima.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T17:44:47-02:00</updated>
    <id>https://rodrigodlima.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve always wanted to have my blog and publish things I want, especially in the IT area, since I&rsquo;ve been working for some time as an Infrastructure Analyst, and I&rsquo;ve been through a lot of things that would be interesting to share and also some things of personal interest and some hobbies, such as travel tips, sports, etc. ;-)
However, I was always annoyed having to create an infrastructure to publish anything simple, even a text.
I always had to set up a Wordpress instance, an Apache, etc. And it was even more work to write a post in a standardized and simple way.
That&rsquo;s when one day while researching some technologies I read something about Octopress. Before reading, I thought: Well, it must be another &ldquo;Wordpress&rdquo; or Wiki type. But I was wrong. I started reading some characteristics of Octopress and I already saw that the proposal was different, as it is a framework for generating static pages and with fantastic integration with Github, without the need to hire a VPS to host your blog.
How wonderful, I decided to test it. Well, I can say it&rsquo;s not a very simple configuration, it took me about two days to &ldquo;understand&rdquo; how it works and to make it work. But after it&rsquo;s ready, I can say: It&rsquo;s worth every minute lost in the configuration.
Now, in just a few minutes I generate a new post, version it, and best of all, in plain text, without HTML, Javascripts, Templates, etc&hellip;</p>

<p>As this is the first post and my environment is still in &ldquo;Beta&rdquo; phase, there is still a lot to improve.</p>

<p>I used CentOS 7 and Fedora 20 as Operating Systems and there are some &ldquo;workarounds&rdquo; to make Octopress work, and as soon as I get more familiar with it I will post explaining how to do the configuration.</p>

<p>See you soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
